[
	{"id":0,"question":"In Genesis 1:2 what moved over the surface of the waters?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"The Spirit of God"},{"id":2,"text":"Darkness"},{"id":3,"text":"Wind"},{"id":3,"text":"The glory of God"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"The Spirit of God (Genesis 1:2)"}]},
	{"id":1,"question":"In Genesis 1:14 God creates the sun and moon for what purpose?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"For seasons, days and years"},{"id":2,"text":"To give light on the earth"},{"id":3,"text":"As navigational guides"},{"id":3,"text":"To control the tides and to warm the earth"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"For seasons, days and years (Genesis 1:14)"}]},
	{"id":2,"question":"According to Genesis 2:5 why was no shrub of the field yet in the earth?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"God had not sent rain upon the earth"},{"id":2,"text":"God had yet to create plants"},{"id":3,"text":"God had not cultivated the ground"},{"id":3,"text":"Water had yet to be gathered in one place so there was no dry ground"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"God had not sent rain upon the earth (Genesis 2:5)"}]},
	{"id":3,"question":"The river that flowed out of Eden divided into how many rivers?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"4"},{"id":2,"text":"3"},{"id":3,"text":"2"},{"id":3,"text":"7"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"4 (Genesis 2:10)"}]},
	{"id":4,"question":"According to Genesis 2:20 which creatures did Adam not name?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Creatures of the Sea"},{"id":2,"text":"Birds of the air"},{"id":3,"text":"Beasts of the field"},{"id":3,"text":"Cattle"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Creatures of the Sea (Genesis 2:20)"}]},
	{"id":5,"question":"How does Genesis 3:6 describe the tree of the knowledge of good and evil?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A delight to the eyes"},{"id":2,"text":"In the middle of the garden"},{"id":3,"text":"Abounding with many kinds of fruit"},{"id":3,"text":"Could make one like God"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A delight to the eyes (Genesis 3:6)"}]},
	{"id":6,"question":"Acording to Genesis 3:8 why did Adam and Eve hide from God?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"They heard God walking in the garden"},{"id":2,"text":"They heard God calling them"},{"id":3,"text":"They were ashamed because they were naked"},{"id":3,"text":"They were afraid because they had sinned"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"They heard God walking in the garden (Genesis 3:8)"}]},
	{"id":7,"question":"According to Genesis 4:2, Abel was what?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A keeper of flocks"},{"id":2,"text":"A tiller of the ground"},{"id":3,"text":"A deceiver of his brother"},{"id":3,"text":"A manchild of Eve"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A keeper of flocks (Genesis 4:2)"}]},
	{"id":8,"question":"Where did Cain move to after killing his brother Abel?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"East of Eden, in the land of Nod"},{"id":2,"text":"West of Eden, in the land of Edom"},{"id":3,"text":"East of Eden, in the land of Ur"},{"id":3,"text":"West of Eden, in the land of Nod"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"East of Eden, in the land of Nod (Genesis 4:16)"}]},
	{"id":9,"question":"How old was Adam when Seth was born?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"130"},{"id":2,"text":"30"},{"id":3,"text":"100"},{"id":3,"text":"40"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"130 (Genesis 5:3)"}]},
	{"id":10,"question":"How old did Adam live?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"930"},{"id":2,"text":"630"},{"id":3,"text":"920"},{"id":3,"text":"690"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"930 (Genesis 5:5)"}]},
	{"id":11,"question":"Who was Lamech's son?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Noah"},{"id":2,"text":"Methuselah"},{"id":3,"text":"Enoch"},{"id":3,"text":"Jared"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Noah (Genesis 5:29)"}]},
	{"id":12,"question":"Who were the sons of Noah?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Shem, Ham, and Japheth"},{"id":2,"text":"Sham, Ham, and Japheth"},{"id":3,"text":"Shem, Hem, and Japheth"},{"id":3,"text":"Shem, Ham, and Jepheth"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Shem, Ham, and Japheth (Genesis 5:32)"}]},
	{"id":13,"question":"How big was the ark God instructed Noah to build?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"300 cubits long, 50 cubits wide, 30 cubits high"},{"id":2,"text":"200 cubits long, 100 cubits wide, 50 cubits high"},{"id":3,"text":"300 cubits long, 150 cubits wide, 60 cubits high"},{"id":3,"text":"150 cubits long, 75 cubits wide, 20 cubits high"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"300 cubits long, 50 cubits wide, 30 cubits high (Genesis 6:15)"}]},
	{"id":14,"question":"God instructed Noah to build the ark with how many levels?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"3"},{"id":2,"text":"4"},{"id":3,"text":"6"},{"id":3,"text":"5"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"3 (Genesis 6:16)"}]},
	{"id":15,"question":"How many \"clean\" animals was Noah instructed to bring on the ark?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"14"},{"id":2,"text":"2"},{"id":3,"text":"4"},{"id":3,"text":"6"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"14 - 7 pairs of male and female (Genesis 7:2)"}]},
	{"id":16,"question":"How old was Noah when the flood waters came upon the earth?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"600"},{"id":2,"text":"630"},{"id":3,"text":"700"},{"id":3,"text":"693"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"600 (Genesis 7:6)"}]},
	{"id":17,"question":"In Genesis, Flood waters covered the mountains by how much?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"15 cubits"},{"id":2,"text":"25 cubits"},{"id":3,"text":"35 cubits"},{"id":3,"text":"45 cubits"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"15 cubits (Genesis 7:20)"}]},
	{"id":18,"question":"According to Genesis 7:24, how long did the flood waters prevail upon the earth?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"150 days"},{"id":2,"text":"40 days and 40 nights"},{"id":3,"text":"100 days"},{"id":3,"text":"120 days"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"150 days (Genesis 7:24)"}]},
	{"id":19,"question":"Which mountain did Noah's ark find its resting place when the water decreased?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Mount Ararat"},{"id":2,"text":"Mount Sinai"},{"id":3,"text":"Mount of Olives"},{"id":3,"text":"Mount Carmel"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Mount Ararat (Genesis 8:4)"}]},
	{"id":20,"question":"When Noah sent out a dove for the second time, what did it return with in its beak?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"An olive leaf"},{"id":2,"text":"An olive branch"},{"id":3,"text":"An olive"},{"id":3,"text":"An olive flower"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"An olive leaf (Genesis 8:11)"}]},
	{"id":21,"question":"God gave humanity permission to do what after the flood?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Eat meat"},{"id":2,"text":"Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the earth"},{"id":3,"text":"Eat meat with its blood in it"},{"id":3,"text":"Eat unclean animals"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Eat meat (Genesis 9:3)"}]},
	{"id":22,"question":"Noah's son Ham was the father of what nation?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Canaanites"},{"id":2,"text":"Ammonites"},{"id":3,"text":"Hammonites"},{"id":3,"text":"Edomites"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Canaanites (Genesis 9:18)"}]},
	{"id":23,"question":"After the flood what did Noah farm?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Grapes"},{"id":2,"text":"Figs"},{"id":3,"text":"Wheat"},{"id":3,"text":"Olives"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Grapes (Genesis 9:20)"}]},
	{"id":24,"question":"How old did Noah live?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"950"},{"id":2,"text":"940"},{"id":3,"text":"900"},{"id":3,"text":"970"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"950 (Genesis 9:29)"}]},
	{"id":25,"question":"In Genesis 10, Nimrod was known as what?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A mighty hunter before the Lord"},{"id":2,"text":"A masterful musician before the Lord"},{"id":3,"text":"A mighty warrior before the Lord"},{"id":3,"text":"A mighty builder before the Lord"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A mighty hunter before the Lord (Genesis 10:8-9)"}]},
	{"id":26,"question":"The tower of Babel was constructed where?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"The land of Shinar"},{"id":2,"text":"The land of Shelah"},{"id":3,"text":"The land of Sinite"},{"id":3,"text":"The land of Raamah"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"The land of Shinar (Genesis 11:2)"}]},
	{"id":27,"question":"Who was Abram's father?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Terah"},{"id":2,"text":"Nahor"},{"id":3,"text":"Haran"},{"id":3,"text":"Eber"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Terah (Genesis 11:27)"}]},
	{"id":28,"question":"Where was Abram living when God said to him \"Go forth from your country\"?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Haran"},{"id":2,"text":"Ur"},{"id":3,"text":"Moreh"},{"id":3,"text":"Shechem"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Haran (Genesis 11:31)"}]},
	{"id":29,"question":"Why did Abram go to Egypt in Genesis 12?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Famine in the land"},{"id":2,"text":"God told him to go there"},{"id":3,"text":"Armies were pursuing him"},{"id":3,"text":"To buy and trade"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Famine in the land (Genesis 12:10)"}]},
	{"id":30,"question":"In Genesis 12, why did God strike Pharaoh with great plagues?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Because of Sarai, Abram's wife"},{"id":2,"text":"Because Pharaoh would not let God's people go"},{"id":3,"text":"Because he gave Abram sheep, oxen, and donkeys"},{"id":3,"text":"Because he had made the Israelites slaves"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Because of Sarai, Abram's wife (Genesis 12:17)"}]},
	{"id":31,"question":"Why did Abram and Lot separate in Genesis 13?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Their herdsmen were fighting"},{"id":2,"text":"Lot wanted to go to Sodom"},{"id":3,"text":"Lot wanted to go to Zoar"},{"id":3,"text":"There was a famine and the land could not support them"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Their herdsmen were fighting (Genesis 13:7)"}]},
	{"id":32,"question":"In Genesis 13, Mamre was known for what kind of tree?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Oak trees"},{"id":2,"text":"Cedar trees"},{"id":3,"text":"Sycamore trees"},{"id":3,"text":"Olive trees"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Oaks (Genesis 13:18)"}]},
	{"id":33,"question":"In Genesis 14, what was in the valley of Siddim?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Bitumen pits"},{"id":2,"text":"Bogs and swamps"},{"id":3,"text":"Salt"},{"id":3,"text":"Limestone and Sulphur"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Bitumen pits (Genesis 14:10)"}]},
	{"id":34,"question":"How many fought in the Battle of the Kings in Genesis 14?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Four against five"},{"id":2,"text":"Three against four"},{"id":3,"text":"Five against six"},{"id":3,"text":"Two against three"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Four against five (Genesis 14:9)"}]},
	{"id":35,"question":"How many trained men did Abram take to rescue his nephew Lot?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"318"},{"id":2,"text":"320"},{"id":3,"text":"328"},{"id":3,"text":"118"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"318 (Genesis 14:14)"}]},
	{"id":36,"question":"Melchizedek was the king of what city?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Salem"},{"id":2,"text":"Shaveh"},{"id":3,"text":"Jerusalem"},{"id":3,"text":"Elyon"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Salem (Genesis 14:18)"}]},
	{"id":37,"question":"While childless, who was Abram's only heir?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Eliezer"},{"id":2,"text":"Ishmael"},{"id":3,"text":"Lot"},{"id":3,"text":"Sarai"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Eliezer (Genesis 15:2)"}]},
	{"id":38,"question":"In Genesis 15, God asked Abram to sacrifice a heifer, goat, and ram of what age?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Three years old"},{"id":2,"text":"One year old"},{"id":3,"text":"Newborn"},{"id":3,"text":"Two years old"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"3 years old (Genesis 15:9)"}]},
	{"id":39,"question":"What passed between the cut pieces of Abram's sacrifice in Genesis 15?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A smoking pot and a flaming torch"},{"id":2,"text":"Birds of prey"},{"id":3,"text":"Lightning"},{"id":3,"text":"A flaming sword"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A smoking pot and a flaming torch (Genesis 15:17)"}]},
	{"id":40,"question":"Where was Sarai's servant Hagar from?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Egypt"},{"id":2,"text":"Mesopotamia"},{"id":3,"text":"Haran"},{"id":3,"text":"Canaan"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Egypt (Genesis 16:1)"}]},
	{"id":41,"question":"How does the Angel of the Lord describe Ishmael to Hagar?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A wild donkey of a man"},{"id":2,"text":"A thorn in the side of Abram"},{"id":3,"text":"A peacemaker"},{"id":3,"text":"A mighty warrior in battle"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A wild donkey of a man (Genesis 16:12)"}]},
	{"id":42,"question":"What is the meaning of Abraham's name?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Father of a multitude"},{"id":2,"text":"Exalted father"},{"id":3,"text":"Father of the stars"},{"id":3,"text":"Father of promise"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Father of a multitude (Genesis 17:5)"}]},
	{"id":43,"question":"What time of day does Genesis 18 say Abraham was visited by three men?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"In the heat of the day"},{"id":2,"text":"In the cool of the morning"},{"id":3,"text":"In the twilight of the evening"},{"id":3,"text":"In the cool of the night"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"In the heat of the day (Genesis 18:1)"}]},
	{"id":44,"question":"Why did Abraham bring water to his three visitors by the Oaks of Mamre?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"To wash their feet"},{"id":2,"text":"To give them a drink"},{"id":3,"text":"To wash their hands"},{"id":3,"text":"To give their camels a drink"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"To wash their feet (Genesis 18:4)"}]},
	{"id":45,"question":"What city did Lot escape to when fleeing the destruction of Sodom?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Zoar"},{"id":2,"text":"Babel"},{"id":3,"text":"Sidon"},{"id":3,"text":"Admah"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Zoar (Genesis 19:22)"}]},
	{"id":46,"question":"How many daughters did Lot have?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"2"},{"id":2,"text":"3"},{"id":3,"text":"4"},{"id":3,"text":"1"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"2 (Genesis 19:30)"}]},
	{"id":47,"question":"After God destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah, Lot was afraid to live in Zoar, so he lived where?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"In a cave"},{"id":2,"text":"In the valley"},{"id":3,"text":"On the hillside"},{"id":3,"text":"In a forest"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"In a cave (Genesis 19:30)"}]},
	{"id":48,"question":"How many times did Abram/Abraham claim his wife was his sister?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Two times"},{"id":2,"text":"None"},{"id":3,"text":"One time"},{"id":3,"text":"Three times"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Two times (Genesis 12:13 & 20:2)"}]},
	{"id":49,"question":"God speaks to Abimelech in a dream and describes Abraham to him as what?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A prophet"},{"id":2,"text":"A king"},{"id":3,"text":"A patriarch"},{"id":3,"text":"A chosen one"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A prophet (Genesis 20:7)"}]},
	{"id":50,"question":"How old was Abraham when Isaac was born?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"100"},{"id":2,"text":"99"},{"id":3,"text":"101"},{"id":3,"text":"110"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"100 (Genesis 21:5)"}]},
	{"id":51,"question":"When Abraham and Sarah sent Hagar away, where did she go?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"The wilderness of Beersheba"},{"id":2,"text":"The wilderness of Shur"},{"id":3,"text":"The wilderness of Paranoias"},{"id":3,"text":"The wilderness of Midbar"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"The wilderness of Beersheba (Genesis 21:14)"}]},
	{"id":52,"question":"What did the servants of Abimelech take from Abraham?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A well of water"},{"id":2,"text":"Seven ewe lambs"},{"id":3,"text":"Sarah his wife"},{"id":3,"text":"3 camels"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A well of water (Genesis 21:22)"}]},
	{"id":53,"question":"When Ishmael grew older, he became what?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"An archer"},{"id":2,"text":"A farmer"},{"id":3,"text":"A sheepherder"},{"id":3,"text":"A vinedresser"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"An archer (Genesis 21:20)"}]},
	{"id":54,"question":"What did Abraham plant at Beersheba?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A tamarisk tree"},{"id":2,"text":"An acacia tree"},{"id":3,"text":"A balsam tree"},{"id":3,"text":"A fig tree"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A tamarisk tree (Genesis 21:33)"}]},
	{"id":55,"question":"Where did God instruct Abraham to go to offer Isaac as a sacrifice?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Land of Moriah"},{"id":2,"text":"Land of Megiddo"},{"id":3,"text":"Land of Kadesh"},{"id":3,"text":"Land of Shechem"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Land of Moriah (Genesis 22:2)"}]},
	{"id":56,"question":"Who was Buz in relation to Abraham?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Nephew"},{"id":2,"text":"Cousin"},{"id":3,"text":"Brother"},{"id":3,"text":"Grandson"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Nephew (Genesis 22:21)"}]},
	{"id":57,"question":"How old did Sarah live?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"127"},{"id":2,"text":"120"},{"id":3,"text":"112"},{"id":3,"text":"117"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"127 (Genesis 23:1)"}]},
	{"id":58,"question":"Where did Sarah die?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Hebron"},{"id":2,"text":"Beersheba"},{"id":3,"text":"Bethel"},{"id":3,"text":"Shechem"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Hebron (Genesis 23:2)"}]},
	{"id":59,"question":"Where did Abraham bury Sarah?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"The cave of Machpelah"},{"id":2,"text":"The field of Mamre"},{"id":3,"text":"The valley of Ephron"},{"id":3,"text":"The tombs of Haran"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"The cave of Machpelah (Genesis 23:9)"}]},
	{"id":60,"question":"Abraham's servant gave Rebekah two bracelets, weighing how much?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"10 gold shekels"},{"id":2,"text":"Half a shekel each"},{"id":3,"text":"5 gold shekels"},{"id":3,"text":"10 gold shekels each"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"10 gold shekels (Genesis 24:22)"}]},
	{"id":61,"question":"What was Issac doing when he saw Rebekah for the first time?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Meditating in the field"},{"id":2,"text":"Ploughing the field"},{"id":3,"text":"Harvesting the field"},{"id":3,"text":"Resting under a tree"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Meditating in the field (Genesis 24:63)"}]},
	{"id":62,"question":"After Sarah died, Abraham took another wife. What was her name?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Keturah"},{"id":2,"text":"Shuah"},{"id":3,"text":"Bilhah"},{"id":3,"text":"Deborah"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Keturah (Genesis 25:1)"}]},
	{"id":63,"question":"How old was Issac when he married Rebekah?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"40"},{"id":2,"text":"30"},{"id":3,"text":"25"},{"id":3,"text":"35"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"40 (Genesis 25:20)"}]},
	{"id":64,"question":"What did the Lord prophetically say to Rebekah about the twins in her womb?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"The older shall serve the younger"},{"id":2,"text":"One will be hairy, one will not"},{"id":3,"text":"One will be a deceiver, one will be deceived"},{"id":3,"text":"The older shall bless the younger"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"The older shall serve the younger (Genesis 25:23)"}]},
	{"id":65,"question":"How many years was Rebekah barren in her marriage with Isaac?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"20"},{"id":2,"text":"10"},{"id":3,"text":"5"},{"id":3,"text":"25"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"20 (Genesis 25:26b)"}]},
	{"id":66,"question":"Where did Jacob like to spend his time?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"In his tent"},{"id":2,"text":"In the field"},{"id":3,"text":"By the river"},{"id":3,"text":"In the forest"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"In his tent (Genesis 25:27)"}]},
	{"id":67,"question":"What did the Philistines do to Isaac out of envy?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Filled Abraham's wells with dirt"},{"id":2,"text":"Stole Isaac's livestock"},{"id":3,"text":"Captured Isaac's relatives"},{"id":3,"text":"Burned Isaac's fields"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Filled Abraham's wells with dirt (Genesis 26:15)"}]},
	{"id":68,"question":"What meal did Rebekah prepare for Jacob to deceive Isaac?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Two young goats"},{"id":2,"text":"Two young sheep"},{"id":3,"text":"Two young calves"},{"id":3,"text":"Two young deer"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Two young goats (Genesis 27:9)"}]},
	{"id":69,"question":"Where did Jacob flee after cheating Esau of his birthright?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"To his uncle Laban in Haran"},{"id":2,"text":"To his uncle Nahor in Hazor"},{"id":3,"text":"To his uncle Lot in Ur"},{"id":3,"text":"To his uncle Haran in Lebanon"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"To his uncle Laban in Haran (Genesis 27:43)"}]},
	{"id":70,"question":"Why did Rebekah say she loathed her life?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Because of the Hittite women"},{"id":2,"text":"Because Esau wanted to kill Jacob"},{"id":3,"text":"Because Isaac was bitter towards Rebekah for helping Jacob"},{"id":3,"text":"Because Jacob had to flee to Haran"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Because of the Hittite women (Genesis 27:46)"}]},
	{"id":71,"question":"What did Jacob do with the stone that he used as a pillow?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Poured oil on it"},{"id":2,"text":"Placed it in the middle of the river as a memorial"},{"id":3,"text":"Sacrificed a lamb on it"},{"id":3,"text":"Carried the stone with him to Haran"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Poured oil on it (Genesis 28:18)"}]},
	{"id":72,"question":"When Jacob first met Rachel, what did she bring with her?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Sheep"},{"id":2,"text":"Camels"},{"id":3,"text":"Bread"},{"id":3,"text":"Animal skins with water"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Sheep (Genesis 29:6)"}]},
	{"id":73,"question":"What did Jacob do after he kissed Rachel for the first time?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Cried"},{"id":2,"text":"Sang a song"},{"id":3,"text":"Realized it was her sister Leah"},{"id":3,"text":"Watered her father Laban's flock"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Cried (Genesis 29:12)"}]},
	{"id":74,"question":"What was undesirable about Laban's daughter Leah?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Her eyes were weak"},{"id":2,"text":"Her hand was withered"},{"id":3,"text":"She was unable to bear children"},{"id":3,"text":"She was haughty and proud"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Her eyes were weak (Genesis 29:17)"}]},
	{"id":75,"question":"What did Laban give Rachel and Jacob as a wedding gift?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"His female servant"},{"id":2,"text":"Livestock"},{"id":3,"text":"Gold bracelets and rings"},{"id":3,"text":"A parcel of land"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"His female servant (Genesis 29:29)"}]},
	{"id":76,"question":"How many years did Jacob serve Laban in total?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"20 years"},{"id":2,"text":"14 years"},{"id":3,"text":"7 years"},{"id":3,"text":"12 years"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"20 years (Genesis 31:41)"}]},
	{"id":77,"question":"What did Leah's son Reuben bring in from the wheat harvest that Rachel desperately wanted?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Mandrakes"},{"id":2,"text":"Myrrh"},{"id":3,"text":"Coriander"},{"id":3,"text":"Bdellium"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Mandrakes (Genesis 30:14)"}]},
	{"id":78,"question":"How did Laban come to believe that God had blessed him because of Jacob?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"By divination"},{"id":2,"text":"God told him"},{"id":3,"text":"Jacob told him"},{"id":3,"text":"It was told him in a dream"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"By divination (Genesis 30:27)"}]},
	{"id":79,"question":"How many times did Laban change Jacob's wages?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"10"},{"id":2,"text":"4"},{"id":3,"text":"7"},{"id":3,"text":"14"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"10 (Genesis 31:7)"}]},
	{"id":80,"question":"What did Rachel steal from her father, Laban, when she left home with her husband Jacob?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Laban's household gods"},{"id":2,"text":"Laban's money"},{"id":3,"text":"Laban's household jewels"},{"id":3,"text":"Laban's favourite camel"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Laban's household gods (Genesis 31:34)"}]},
	{"id":81,"question":"When Jacob returned ot Esau after 20 years, how many men did Esau meet him with?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"400"},{"id":2,"text":"200"},{"id":3,"text":"300"},{"id":3,"text":"140"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"400 (Genesis 32:6)"}]},
	{"id":82,"question":"How did Rachel die?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"In childbirth"},{"id":2,"text":"Of old age"},{"id":3,"text":"Killed by Hamor"},{"id":3,"text":"Of dehydration in the wilderness"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"In childbirth - to Benjamin (Genesis 35:18)"}]},
	{"id":83,"question":"Where was Rachel buried?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Bethlehem"},{"id":2,"text":"Shechem"},{"id":3,"text":"Penuel"},{"id":3,"text":"Succoth"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Bethlehem (Genesis 35:19)"}]},
	{"id":84,"question":"How old did Jacob live?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"180"},{"id":2,"text":"130"},{"id":3,"text":"150"},{"id":3,"text":"140"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"180 (Genesis 35:28)"}]},
	{"id":85,"question":"How did Joseph find his brothers in Dothan?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"A stranger told him where they were"},{"id":2,"text":"His father told him where they were"},{"id":3,"text":"His brothers told him where they would be"},{"id":3,"text":"The sons of Bilhah and Zilpah told him where they were"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"A stranger told him where they were (Genesis 37:17)"}]},
	{"id":86,"question":"Which brother convinced the others not to kill Joseph?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Reuben"},{"id":2,"text":"Judah"},{"id":3,"text":"Simeon"},{"id":3,"text":"Issachar"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Reuben (Genesis 37:22)"}]},
	{"id":87,"question":"Rather than kill him, Joseph's brothers sold him to who?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Midianite traders"},{"id":2,"text":"Amalekite traders"},{"id":3,"text":"Edomite traders"},{"id":3,"text":"Moabite traders"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Midianite traders (Genesis 37:28)"}]},
	{"id":88,"question":"Who was Potiphar?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"An officer of Pharaoh"},{"id":2,"text":"A wealthy merchant"},{"id":3,"text":"Pharaoh's cupbearer"},{"id":3,"text":"A businessman"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"An officer of Pharaoh (Genesis 37:36)"}]},
	{"id":89,"question":"Who told Joseph a dream while in prison?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Pharaoh's cupbearer and baker"},{"id":2,"text":"Pharaoh's cupbearer and butler"},{"id":3,"text":"Pharaoh's gardener and head chef"},{"id":3,"text":"Pharaoh's captain of the guard"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Pharaoh's cupbearer and baker (Genesis 40:8)"}]},
	{"id":90,"question":"On what occasion was the cupbearer restored to his position?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Pharaoh's birthday"},{"id":2,"text":"Wag and Thoth Festival"},{"id":3,"text":"Tekh Festival"},{"id":3,"text":"The birth of Pharaoh's son"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"His birthday (Genesis 40:20)"}]},
	{"id":91,"question":"How long did the cupbearer forget Joseph in prison?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"2 years"},{"id":2,"text":"3 years"},{"id":3,"text":"1 year"},{"id":3,"text":"4 years"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"2 years (Genesis 40:23-41:1)"}]},
	{"id":92,"question":"In Pharaoh's dream how many cows came up out of the Nile?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"14"},{"id":2,"text":"7"},{"id":3,"text":"6"},{"id":3,"text":"10"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"14 - 7 fat cows + 7 skinny cows (Genesis 41:2-3)"}]},
	{"id":93,"question":"What was the first thing Joseph did before he was brought to interpret Pharaoh's dream?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Shaved"},{"id":2,"text":"Ate"},{"id":3,"text":"Washed his feet"},{"id":3,"text":"Combed his hair"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Shaved (Genesis 41:14)"}]},
	{"id":94,"question":"Of the Egyptian harvest how much did Joseph instruct be stored for the famine?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"One-fifth"},{"id":2,"text":"One-third"},{"id":3,"text":"One-half"},{"id":3,"text":"One-sixth"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"One-fifth (Genesis 41:34)"}]},
	{"id":95,"question":"How did Joseph's brothers travel to Egypt?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Donkeys"},{"id":2,"text":"Camels"},{"id":3,"text":"Horses"},{"id":3,"text":"On foot"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Donkeys (Genesis 42:26)"}]},
	{"id":96,"question":"What gift did Joseph give Benjamin after he had revealed himself to his brothers?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"300 shekels of silver and 5 changes of clothes"},{"id":2,"text":"100 shekels of silver"},{"id":3,"text":"A silver cup"},{"id":3,"text":"10 donkeys each loaded with grain"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"300 shekels of silver and 5 changes of clothes (Genesis 45:22)"}]},
	{"id":97,"question":"How old was Jacob when he spoke to Pharaoh? ?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"130"},{"id":2,"text":"120"},{"id":3,"text":"100"},{"id":3,"text":"140"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"130 (Genesis 47:9)"}]},
	{"id":98,"question":"Who sold their land to Pharaoh in exchange for food?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"All the Egyptians"},{"id":2,"text":"Jacob's family"},{"id":3,"text":"The people of Goshen"},{"id":3,"text":"Egyptian priests"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"All the Egyptians (Genesis 47:20)"}]},
	{"id":99,"question":"Who was Jacob's firstborn?","choices":[{"id":1,"text":"Reuben"},{"id":2,"text":"Simeon"},{"id":3,"text":"Levi"},{"id":3,"text":"Judah"}],"answer":[{"id":1,"explanation":"Reuben (Genesis 49:3)"}]}
]